Good morning.
Hope you all are doing well.
That's wonderful.
So glad.
For those of you that I have not had the privilege of meeting, my name is Ryan, and I am one
of the pastors here.
I am so grateful that you all have made the time to join us.
I pray regularly as I come to church.
On my way to church, I'm just so thankful for what I call you all my family, my spiritual
family.
So many of you are such an encouragement to me, and I know I watch you all encourage one
another, and I'm so blessed by that, and just grateful to be a part of this community.
So thank you.
We are entering a new series that we talked about a few months ago.
I asked you for questions that you might have about the Bible.
Does anyone remember me asking you for questions about the Bible?
Okay.
I received over 20 questions about the Bible, which is wonderful, which I won't be able
to answer all of them.
Some of you that I know I couldn't get to have reached out to you individually.
We've had some discussions about some of those.
I'm going to do my best, and I'm going to keep the rest of them for future opportunities.
And so I just want to make sure we know I'm not going to be able to answer all the questions.
But I was honestly kind of shocked by the questions that I received, and shocked in a good way.
Because I don't know if I'm like, I don't know, I'm usually an optimist, but for whatever
reason, I felt like I was going to get gotcha questions on like hot topic cultural issues.
Like I thought you guys were going to back me into a corner and make me try and weasel
myself out of that corner.
I don't know.
I just talked about how wonderfully encouraging ours is a spiritual family.
And then when I asked you to give me questions about the Bible, I assumed that you were going
to put me in a corner, and you didn't.
I don't know if that's just out of love for your pastor or out of a wantingness, a desire
that our church doesn't fall apart in one sermon series.
I don't know why you chose not to do that, but I'm so thankful that you did.
And I really, I kind of received two different types of questions, which were super encouraging
to me as a pastor.
The first type of question that I received is like, I received some really base level
Christian questions from new believers or people that aren't even yet believers that
are kind of following this journey of figuring out who Jesus is.
And they asked some really good basic questions about faith.
And then another group of people, some of the more mature believers that have been walking
with Jesus for a long time.
You all sent me some nuanced theological questions, and you're thinking critically about complex
questions, which is awesome.
I love that.
It encouraged my heart.
It solidified for me what I already believe to be true about our church, which is that we
are doing church in a way that is accessible for people who are brand new to Christian faith.
They can come in.
They can follow along with what's happening.
They might not always get what we're doing here.
But they understand enough that they can follow along and figure out who this Jesus guy is.
And they have questions about what it looks like to follow him.
And our mature believers, they don't want oversimplified black and white answers to complex questions.
Which I've been a part of churches where people would just give me the black and white answer.
Just tell me what's right.
Tell me what's wrong.
Don't give me nuance that's difficult, that's challenging.
I don't want any of that.
Just tell, you're the pastor.
You tell me what's right and what's wrong.
And I love, I love that our church family is a church that is willing to kind of live in the tension
and the nuance of the Scriptures.
The Scriptures are tense and nuanced and difficult to understand at times.
So that's what we're going to do for the next few weeks is dive into some of those base level questions
and nuanced theological questions.
And hopefully, my prayer for this whole series is it gives us a much more robust relationship with the Scriptures.
That we have a positive view of what the Scriptures are, what they do for our lives,
what they do to invite us into a relationship with God.
Does that sound good?
All right, well, this week we're not going to answer a question at all.
Because that's what I like to do, right?
I like to say we're going to do something and then do something different.
No, but what we are going to do is we're going to cover what exactly is the Bible.
If we're going to approach the Bible to answer our questions, what is the Bible?
Why does it exist?
And how are we supposed to use it when we answer questions?
When we use the Bible to answer questions, how are we supposed to use it?
So I guess we're actually covering three questions in one.
That sounds ambitious.
So let's pray and then we'll get started.
Father, we are so grateful for your word, both your written word, the Scriptures,
and your living word, Jesus Christ, who is the image of the invisible God,
taken on flesh to show us what it looks like to truly be human,
to truly live in light of your grace and your mercy.
God, may we just, may you just deepen our understanding and our reverence and our love
for this book that you have preserved for us to know salvation through Jesus.
It's in his name I pray.
Amen.
All right.
Does anybody happen to know what this sucker is?
Yell it out if you know what it is.
T, it's a post driver.
Okay.
So it's a post driver.
That's what it is.
Now, does anyone know why it exists?
Why would somebody have created this thing?
For driving posts.
Yes.
Because I don't know if you've ever tried to drive a post before,
but if you did not have a T post driver,
you would hit your hand.
It would hurt.
This makes it easier to drive a post than any other thing that you might use to drive a post.
Yes?
Okay.
Now, you know what it is.
You know why it exists.
Does anybody, most of you might then infer how to use it?
Yeah?
All right.
We got a hole.
Put it over the T post.
We drive it in.
Got it?
Yeah?
Okay.
So what is it?
Why does it exist?
How do we use it?
These are the three most important questions when approaching any tool, right?
We need to know what a tool is,
why it exists,
and how to use it if we're going to use it properly.
And that's what the Bible is, right?
The Bible is a tool.
So if we're going to use it properly,
we need to know what it is,
why it exists,
and how to use it properly.
Because here's the problem.
If you know what a tool is,
and you know how to use it,
but you don't know why it exists,
even when you have a tool, right,
it's still difficult to use.
So if you don't know why it exists,
and the work gets difficult,
the work gets challenging,
but you don't know why it exists,
you might be tempted to give up on the tool
and try and find a different tool
that might work better
to do the thing that you're doing, right?
You've got to understand why the tool exists.
And if you know what something is,
and why it exists,
but you don't know how to use it,
might end up causing a lot of damage along the way.
And the reason I use a T-Post driver as an example
is because the first time I was ever introduced
to one of these tools,
the one that was handed to me to drive post
was severely dented and destroyed
on this kind of top edge.
And I looked at the tool,
and I looked at the guy that handed it to me
and I was like,
what happened here?
And he was like,
well, you know,
there's a guy at our church.
He knew what a T-Post driver was.
He knew why it existed,
but he didn't know how to use it.
And so he spent an hour and a half
trying to drive posts
with the T-Post driver upside down.
And so now he has blistered fingers
and we have a messed up T-Post driver.
So I use that as an illustration
because I think it's important
that we have all three of these questions answered well
when we approach the Bible.
What is it?
Why does it exist?
And how do we use it?
And I'm afraid that whether we realize it or not,
oftentimes we as Christians have answers,
or even if you're new to the faith,
you're questioning Christianity,
you have some presuppositions in your mind
about the answer to those questions.
But what I know as a pastor,
as I interact with people around the Scriptures,
is that our presuppositions are not the same.
Depending on your experience,
depending on the type of church you went to growing up,
or the type of content that you interact with online,
the Scriptures are used in some really diverse ways.
And people define what the Bible is in some diverse ways
and why it exists and how it is to be used.
And so I just want, as a church,
I want us to have kind of a groundwork, a foundation.
And you might think,
okay, shouldn't we have done that like two years ago
when we started church?
Right?
Yeah, we should have.
We should have.
Definitely.
But I think what we all come in here
kind of assuming that we all answer those questions
the same way.
And the reality is,
I've been pastoring the church long enough
and I've had enough conversations with you
that that's not the case.
We all kind of have different lenses
and angles to that question.
So I want to answer those three questions today
in hopes that it will set us up
for the rest of the series moving forward.
That make sense?
Okay, so some of this might feel luxury.
That's okay.
We're just gonna, we're gonna get into it.
We're gonna see where the Holy Spirit
tells me to stop being luxury
and start being pastoral.
And hopefully we get out of here before 1130, okay?
All right.
If you want to turn in your Bibles
to 2 Timothy chapter three,
we're gonna get there eventually
after I finish lecturing some.
Okay, what is the Bible?
What is this thing that we hold in our hands?
Well, it is a masterful collection
of multiple genres of literature
composed and preserved over thousands of years
by the people of ancient Israel and their descendants.
Does anybody know how many volumes exist in the Bible?
66 books, two volumes.
There we go.
I was a trick question.
I asked it in a difficult way.
We've got two volumes, right?
We've got the Old Testament
and we've got the New Testament.
Those two volumes are made up of 66 books
written by 40 different authors.
The first volume is the Old Testament
and we all know,
everybody in here knows how the Old Testament starts, right?
In the beginning,
God created the heavens and the earth.
This is how the first volume starts.
It is an incredibly beautiful depiction
of an infinite God creating a perfect world
for humanity to enjoy and manage
under his loving rule and reign.
And that lasts about how many pages would you say?
Less than one page.
Does the beautiful, incredible design
of a loving creator
creating humanity to live in submission to him,
less than one page does it last?
Humanity rebels.
We choose to run the world
by our own set of rules.
And yet on that same page where we screwed up,
God promises a message of hope.
God promises that he will work through humanity.
You guys have heard this,
Genesis chapter three, right?
Through the seed of a woman.
God is going to work within the context
of human relationships
to bring about salvation
to the rest of the world.
And from there,
the ancient Israelite people
claim that this loving creator
from Genesis chapter one,
who made the world and everything in it,
that he chose the people of Israel
to bring about that salvation,
that he was going to partner with Israel
and they were going to demonstrate
to the entire world
how we could be saved,
how we could be back restored
in right relationship with God.
And now,
this is where things take
an even more challenging
and difficult turn, right?
Because a majority of the rest
of the Old Testament
is Israel telling their history,
their story
in a brutally honest way.
Most of the Old Testament
is this group of people,
these Israelites,
failing to do the thing
that God partnered with them to do.
And the thing that I love,
one of the things that I love most
about the Bible
is the honesty of which,
you guys always,
you've heard that the people
that record history
are in charge of what's said
about history.
So sometimes it's hard
to trust history
when somebody,
like a conquering king
writes his own history book.
It's like,
oh yeah,
you're really painting yourself
in a good light here.
The thing I love about the Bible
is that the Israelites
don't do that.
They're like,
hey,
here's us,
all of our warts,
all of our moles,
all of our failures.
We regularly
and intentionally
failed to do the thing
that God partnered with us
to do.
As this failure continues
on repeat,
along come
the Israelite prophets.
Everybody loves
to read the prophets.
They're easy to understand.
We know exactly
what they're saying.
Black and white,
crystal clear, right?
Well, the prophets,
they warn
the Israelites
that if they continue
to fail,
that God will allow them
to suffer the consequences
of their actions
and they'll be conquered
by the kingdoms
of this world.
And that happens,
right?
Babylonians,
Assyrians,
they come in
and they conquer
the people of Israelite.
These chosen people,
God's chosen people
get conquered
and destroyed
by the secular nations
of the world.
But within the prophets
are included predictions
of a future leader
who would emerge
from the line
of Israel's kings
and he would faithfully
do the thing
that Israel failed to do.
That, my friends,
is the Old Testament.
That's where it ends.
Loving creator
creates a good world.
Humanity rebels,
sends the world
into chaos and death.
God partners
with a specific group
of people
to bring about salvation
to the rest of the world.
They fail
and their leaders predict
a coming leader
who's going to fix it all.
He's going to do the thing
that Israel could never do
and that leader
never shows up
and the Old Testament ends.
Does that sound
like a wonderful story
that we should just
build the foundation
of our life on?
Okay.
Rough ending.
Enter the New Testament.
Fast forward
a few hundred years later.
An Israelite man
who is a descendant
of the ancient Israelite kings
named Jesus
enters the picture.
The circumstances
of his birth
and his life
fulfill hundreds,
hundreds
of Old Testament prophecies
made about the coming leader
in a way
that is statistically impossible.
He begins to do
miraculous things
like heal the sick,
walk on water,
and feed thousands
of people
with one little boy's lunchbox.
He claims
that he is the leader
of this Old Testament narrative,
that he is the point
of the whole story,
and that salvation
of the world
will come through,
wait for it,
his death
and resurrection.
Obviously.
Right?
Isn't that the most obvious
next step
of the story?
No.
Like, everyone thought
he was nuts,
including his closest friends
and followers.
What do you mean
death and resurrection?
We don't see that
in the prophecies
of the Old Testament.
They missed it.
But then it happened.
Exactly how he said it would.
Hundreds of eyewitnesses,
physical eyewitnesses,
saw him die
and then saw him
back to life again,
which sparked
a movement of people
who began to follow Jesus
as the leader,
the one that the Old Testament
was all about,
the promised salvation
for the world.
His earliest
and closest followers,
they began to write down
accounts of everything
that Jesus said and did.
That would be the...
Gospels.
Yep, there we go.
I set you up again.
I need to do better
at setting you up
for answers.
That's my fault.
So we got the Gospels,
his leaders writing down,
his followers writing down
what he said
and what he did
as the movement
of Christ followers grew.
They started to write down
the history of the church,
that's Acts,
and as things got
increasingly challenging
for them,
the leaders of the movement
wrote letters
to the churches.
That would be
the New Testament.
The Gospels, Acts,
the letters
are all combined together.
There you have it.
This is a basic summary
of what the Bible is.
Did any of that
shock any of you?
Okay, I just wasted
all of our time.
It's great.
No, I'm kidding.
This is what the Bible is.
It is a collection
of literature
preserved for us
by the people
of ancient Israel
and all of it,
all of it points
to Jesus,
which begs the question,
okay, so now
why should I care
about this?
If this is just
an ancient book
filled with lots
of different books,
66 different books
compiled together,
why should I care
about this?
Why are there
billions of people
all across the world
right now
gathering together
to read this book,
to pray,
and to sing
to the God
who preserved
this book
for them?
Why?
Because my guess
is that most
of you who have
friends that don't
go to church
are not spending
a majority
of their day
reading an ancient
text and praying
to the God
who preserved
that text for them,
right?
This is a unique
experience that we
as Christians hold,
so why is it
that this book
matters so much
to us?
Well,
luckily for us,
this question
is a bit easier
to answer
than the first
in a short
amount of time.
You could answer
this question
in a bunch
of different ways,
but I would say
this,
if the birth
and life
of one person,
one individual
fulfills hundreds
of prophecies
made by multiple
authors hundreds
of years before
he was born,
and then if
that person
says he's going
to rise from
the dead
and does it,
and it's confirmed
by hundreds
of eyewitnesses
and starts a
global movement
of billions
of people
over thousands
of years,
then any
of us
who are
intellectually
honest
should do
something
with this,
right?
That's a
preposterous
amount of
circumstances
that happen
to bring
this book
together,
and so if
you're in here
and you're
intellectually
honest and
you're not
exactly sure
what this
thing is,
I would make
the case
that you've
got to do
something
with it.
And then for
those of us
that are followers
of Jesus
that have done
something with it,
that have said,
wow,
this book is
miraculous,
this is crazy,
all of the
circumstances
surrounding it,
that this
would exist.
Most of us
in here
who have
considered this
book have
encountered
the incredible
love of a
God who
created us,
who made us,
and it has
changed us
forever.
It's changed
me forever.
So why does it
matter?
It matters
because it
changes people's
lives.
It gives
them hope,
it gives
them a
future,
it answers
the most
significant
questions about
life in the
most complex
ways.
Nowhere else
have I found
a complex
set of
answers to
the most
intrinsic
questions of
humanity.
And if you're
in here and
that has not
been your
experience with
the Bible,
if you're
like,
look,
Ryan,
I've tried
it,
I'm an
intellectually
honest person,
I've wrestled
with the text,
but it does
not do for me
what you're
saying it does
for you,
is it
possible that
it's been
misused in
your life?
That somebody's
used it in
the wrong way
to explain
something that
was never
meant to be
explained by
the Scriptures
to begin
with?
Is it
possible that
you just
don't have
the right
tools to
read it in
the way that
it was
intended to
be read?
Is it
possible that
the reason
you keep
banging your
head against
the wall
or getting
angry with
the God
you find
in these
pages is
that you
just don't
have the
tools to
read it the
way that
it was
intended to
be read?
I see this
all the time
with people
who are
struggling with
the Christian
faith.
Those of us
that have
been followers
of Jesus
for a long
time but
run into
complex
questions that
we don't
have answers
to.
Is it
possible that
we might
just not have
the tools
necessary?
Is it
possible that
we're reading
the Bible
in a way
was never
intended
intended to
be read?
Is it
possible that
we're using
the tool
in the
wrong way?
Right?
How much
damage can
be caused
in our
life and
in the
lives of
those around
us if we
don't know
how the
tool is
meant to
be used?
All right.
That leads
me to the
third and
final question
which is the
question we're
going to spend
most of our
time on and
that is
how is
the Bible
intended to
be used?
Just like
any other
tool there
are ways the
Bible is
intended to
be used
in ways
that it
isn't.
Many of us
in here we've
probably been
hurt or seen
others hurt
when the
Bible gets
misused or
manipulated or
weaponized for
a very specific
agenda.
Well the
good news is
the Bible
actually gives
us some
insight on how
it's supposed
to be used.
So we
should ask
it the
question.
We shouldn't
come from the
outside and
say this is
how it's
supposed to
be used.
How does
the Bible
say it's
supposed to
be used?
2 Timothy
chapter 3
starting in
verse 14.
Paul says
this,
but you
Timothy
must remain
faithful to
the things
that you
have been
taught.
You know
that they
are true
for you
know you
can trust
those who
taught you.
You have
been taught
the holy
Scriptures from
childhood and
they have
given you the
wisdom to
receive salvation
that comes
from trusting
in Christ.
All Scripture
is inspired
by God and
it is useful
to teach us
what is true
to make us
realize what is
wrong in our
lives.
It corrects us
when we are
wrong and
teaches us what
to do right.
God uses it to
prepare and
equip his
people to
do every
good work.
that's what
the Scripture
says about
itself.
These are
some of
Paul's
final words
to his
protege
Timothy
and they
are in
response to
a group
of people
that are
actually
misusing
the Scriptures
to lead
people astray.
Timothy
is dealing
with false
teachers who
are misusing
the Scriptures
and Paul
reminds
Timothy
in this
short
passage
what the
Bible is
and how
it is
intended
to be
used.
I see
kind of
three
things in
here about
the Bible
that help
us figure
out how
it's meant
to be
used.
The first
is that
Paul talks
about the
story of
the Bible.
Verse 14
and 15.
Well in 15
he says
you've been
taught the
holy Scriptures
from childhood
and they have
given you
the wisdom
to receive
the salvation
that comes
by trusting
in Christ.
Paul's point
here in
this passage
it's clear
to me
that he's
saying the
Scriptures
all of the
but right
now we're
talking about
the Old
Testament
right?
Because this
is all
that Timothy
has.
Timothy
has the
Old
Testament
these
are his
Scriptures
and Paul
is saying
Timothy
the Scriptures
the Old
Testament
the whole
point
of the Old
Testament
is that
it's one
unified
story
pointing
you to
salvation
in Jesus.
It's a
unified story
that's all
about
Jesus.
Jesus is
the focal
point
of the
Old
Testament
story
and the
foundation
for the
new.
He is
the word
of God
who became
flesh
and dwelt
among us.
He is the
one true
Israelite
who was
faithful to
do the
thing
that Israel
agreed to
do but
never
could.
And his
one act
of obedience
made salvation
available to
all of us.
So when we
approach the
Old Testament
we've got to
realize that
it's one
grand
narrative.
It's one
epic story.
unified story.
And the goal
of that
story is
to introduce
people to
the salvation
that can be
found in
Jesus and
Jesus alone.
But what
happens is we
tend to kind of
just pick and
choose passages.
And so it's
fall, right?
Fall's upon us.
Fall in the
Miller House means
Harry Potter season.
Anybody else?
Am I the only one?
Okay, some of us,
right?
I'm kind of new
to the Harry Potter
world.
Marissa's like
indoctrinated me.
But what happened
for a while is
that like I
hadn't fully
bought in but
I wanted to
spend time with
my wife so
when she put
Harry Potter
on I'd
watch it.
But we
weren't
watching them
in order,
right?
And so like I
was like asking
her all kinds of
ridiculous questions
like what's this?
This guy's a bad
guy, right?
She's like no,
he's a good
guy.
And I'm like
what?
How is that
guy a good
guy and that
guy's a bad
guy?
And like I'm
getting all
confused throughout
the narrative,
right?
But now that I've
seen all of them
in order,
I can now go
back and I can
watch them out
of order and I
can understand
the unified
narrative.
I get where
we're at in
the thing,
right?
And I share
that because I
think what I
see so many
people do is
they hop into
the Old
Testament without
an understanding
of the unified
story.
We grab bits
and pieces,
we read things
out of context
and we get
confused and
we get angry
and we get
frustrated because
it doesn't seem
to make sense
in certain parts
but what we
have to do
is realize that
it's meant to
be read as a
unified story.
The whole thing
is meant to
point us to
Jesus and when
we can step
back from that
then we can
get into
specific texts
and passages
of Scripture
and say okay
what's going
on here and
how does this
help me
understand more
about who
Jesus is,
about who I
am in
relationship to
God.
Does that
make sense?
We see this
Jesus on the
road to Emmaus
after his
resurrection,
he runs
into some
people who
are steeped
in the Old
Testament.
They were
early disciples
of Jesus.
They know the
Old Testament
inside and
out and yet
when Jesus
died, they
were perplexed.
This is not
what was supposed
to happen.
This is the
Israelite leader
that God promised
from the very
beginning.
He was the
one who was
going to come
and do the
thing God
said and then
he died and
now we're
confused and
we're perplexed
and Jesus shows
up on the road
to Emmaus
with them
and this is
what it says
in Luke
chapter 24
verse 27
Jesus says
and beginning
with Moses
and all the
prophets,
all of the
Old Testament,
he explained
to them what
was said in
all the
Scriptures
concerning
himself.
So if we're
not careful,
we can spend
our lives
like reading
and understanding
the Scriptures
and totally
missed the
entire point.
That's what
these followers
had done.
They had been
steeped in the
Scriptures and
they missed the
point and Jesus
says let me
show you from
the beginning
to the end
how this whole
thing is about
me.
Whenever we
approach the
Bible or use
it to answer
our most
difficult and
pressing
questions,
we have to
understand what
it is and
what it isn't.
It is a
unified story
with one
major plot
line.
If we aren't
careful, we can
easily start to
use this book
like a
theological
textbook.
We just flip
to a certain
chapter and a
certain verse
and we read
a certain
paragraph and
we say this
thing must be
true about
God because
this paragraph
says so.
Well, this
paragraph is
one paragraph
in one
large book
which is
connected to
multiple books
which is
connected to
one unified
story.
So we've
just got to
be careful.
I'm not
saying we
can't just
read one
paragraph and
learn something
about God.
What I'm
saying is we
have to be
careful to
have the
grand
narrative of
Scripture in
our minds
whenever we
approach any
passage of
Scripture.
Does that
make sense?
When we use
the Bible like a
theology textbook we
can end up getting
stuck asking the
wrong questions or
getting in heated
debates over
questions the
author never
intended us to
ask.
None of us have
ever been in a
heated debate over
something that didn't
matter in the
Scriptures.
Okay, apparently
apparently that's
just a kid that
went to Bible
college.
Because that's
all that
happened in
Bible college
was arrogant
18 year olds
getting in fights
over things that
the Bible never
intended us to
get in fights
over.
One of my
favorite
illustrations of
this is there
was a famous
theologian a
while back and
many people were
kind of claiming
that he was
progressive, that
he didn't
actually believe
that the Bible
was the word of
God, that he
was kind of just
this liberal
thinker that
used the Bible
to make sense
of the world
more in a
sociological way
than in a
divine revelation
way.
And so somebody
showed up to one
of his lectures
and they had a
gotcha question
lined up because
they wanted him
to say something
that would make
it seem like he
didn't really
think the Bible
was from God.
And if he
answered this
question wrong
then all of the
conservatives would
say see I knew
it, you don't
think the Bible
is true, we're
not going to
listen to anything
you say.
And so here's
the question.
Okay, they show
up to his lecture
and they say was
the snake in the
garden, the
beginning in
Genesis, the
snake that
talks, was
this a literal
snake that
actually talked?
This is a
gotcha question
because if he
says no, it's
symbolic, it's
you know a
narrative, it's
all this, then
the conservatives
are going to be
like see you
don't believe the
Bible is God's
word.
When you start
saying that then
you ignore all
kinds of things
in the Bible
and you're
going to
throw out
half of the
Scriptures because
of that question
but if you say
that it's an
actual literal
talking snake,
every intellectual
progressive in the
room is going to
say you're a
moron, I don't
have, I don't
trust anything.
It's a gotcha
question, right?
And what I love
is that the
theologian does
not take the
bait because he's
smarter than I
ever will be.
I always take
the bait.
They say, is the
snake in the
garden a literal
talking snake?
And he says, the
more important
question to ask is
what did the
snake say?
What did the
And when we
approach the
Bible like a
theology textbook,
we often ask
questions that
really are not the
main point of the
author's intent.
We ask silly
questions like is
the snake literal
or not literal?
and we totally
ignore the fact
that in his
words are the
foundation of
humanity's
rebellion.
And in his
words are a
shadow of
Jesus' faithfulness
in the New
Testament.
See, this story
perfectly illustrates
how using the
Bible as a
textbook can lead
you in a
different direction
than reading the
Bible as a
unified story.
If you get
stuck on whether
or not the
snake is real
or actually
talking, you
might miss the
shadows of the
story to come.
See, the
snake shows up
to Adam and
Eve and
a perfect
luscious
garden.
All the
food, all
of the
drink, everything
that they
could ever
need or want
and the
snake comes
to deceive
them about
God's
trustworthy
character, about
his faithfulness
and they
choose to take
him at his
word and rebel
against God
thousands of
years later.
Not in a
garden filled
with all of
his needs but
in a desert
after fasting
for 40 days.
The same
figure appears
to Jesus with
the same
statements
about God
not being
trustworthy.
If you
want the
world, if
you want
satisfaction, if
life, you
trust me.
And where
Adam and
Eve failed in
a garden full
of all of
their needs and
all of their
resources, Jesus
was faithful in
a desert.
This is how we
read the Bible as
a unified singular
story pointing us
to Jesus.
It's all about
him.
Let's be careful
not to get so
zoomed in to
certain paragraphs
and texts and
ask questions that
the Scripture never
asks us to
intend.
I just want to
end again here
with Paul's
words one more
time.
He's telling
Timothy that all
of the Scriptures
were given to
you to receive
salvation that
comes through
trusting in
Jesus.
This is the
point of the
Old Testament.
This is the
point of the
Scriptures to
point us to
Jesus.
So let's be
careful when we
approach the
Bible that we
do so
understanding it's
intended to tell
one unified
story.
Let's not treat
it like a
textbook but let's
treat it like a
grand narrative
pointing us to
Jesus.
The second thing
this passage
points us to
is the nature
of the Bible.
Verse 16
says all
Scripture is
inspired by
God.
Second thing
that really
impacts how
we view the
Bible is where
it comes from.
What is the
nature of the
Scriptures?
And Paul here
clearly states
that the nature
of the Scriptures
is divine.
It is breathed
out by God.
The literal
phrase here means
God-spirited.
All Scripture is
It's from God.
But here's where
the tension enters
for us, right?
Because in the
first 15 minutes
of my message
I talked about
what the Bible
is.
Did I mention
much of God
in that talk
at all?
Ancient people
of Israel
preserving letters,
right?
This is a human
book.
Isn't it a human
book?
Didn't we just
go over what
the Bible was
and it was all
about humanity
writing down
things?
Yeah?
But now we
turn to 2 Timothy
and Paul says
that all Scripture
is God-spirited,
breathed out.
We feel
a tension here
or am I the
only one?
Is it a human
book or is it
a divine book?
Thank you,
Megan.
Yes.
She goes to
passages.
So if you
want to have
the right
answers to
the hypothetical
questions I
asked, you
should give
passages a try.
All right,
that's my
plug.
Is it divine
or is it
human?
There's a
tension here.
When we
interpret the
Scriptures,
if we aren't
careful, we can
overemphasize one
side of this
partnership over
the other.
We can totally
ignore the human
language and culture
and context that the
books are written
in.
I've heard this
called the golden
tablet view, right?
If we're not
careful, some of us
can view the
Scriptures as if
God dropped this
copy, this fake
leather copy of the
New Living
Translation of the
Bible.
God dropped it in
my lap for me to
read in the
English with no
thought about the
story or the
people that this
story was written
by.
It's the golden
tablet view.
Anybody grow up in
churches that kind
of view the
Scriptures like
this?
Yeah, right?
We would never
say it like that,
but like baked into
how we teach it is
this understanding
that God preserved
this text for us as
Americans in the
21st century.
And we can, if
we're not careful,
totally ignore the
cultural, historical
context, the
linguistics, all of
that that matter when
understanding the
Scriptures.
The opposite end of
the perspective is
where we make
everything cultural
and historical and
we ignore the fact
that God's word
clearly states that
he intended for his
people to read it and
to understand it and
to live in light of
it.
I call this the
doesn't apply to me
view.
Anybody ever interact
with Christians like
this?
You like confront them
about something they're
doing in their life?
They're like, oh,
that's cultural, that
doesn't apply to me.
No?
I'm the only one too?
Cool.
All right.
This happens.
We can overemphasize
one side of the
perspective over the
other.
It is a divine
inspired book
preserved in human
languages, in human
cultures over a
thousand years.
And if we're going
to understand it
properly, we have to
understand it in its
cultural context.
Unfortunately, I
don't have time to
poke holes in both of
these approaches.
So really quickly, I'm
going to poke a hole
in the golden tablet
approach.
Because I think here at
Canvas, I think we
are a people that
really revere the
Scriptures.
That if anything, we're
going to overemphasize
the divinity, then the
humanity.
And if we aren't
careful, many of us can
default to this
approach.
The problem with this
approach is this is not
what the Bible claims to
be.
The Bible does not
claim to be a 66 book
volume that God dropped
from heaven for us to
find somewhere.
It was preserved through
human language and
culture.
It's divinely inspired by
God for us, but he
chose to do so through
human partnerships.
This is how God works.
He works through human
partnerships.
These partnerships were
with authors who spoke
different languages than
us, lived in a different
culture than us, and
they masterfully wrote in
genres that we aren't
fully used to.
Revelation.
Anyone?
When's the last time you
read an apocalyptic book
outside of the book of
Revelation?
It's difficult, right?
This takes some effort and
it takes some work.
Now, this doesn't mean that
the Bible isn't for us or
that it won't lead us to
truth about God, ourselves,
and the world, but it does
mean if we want a robust,
deep understanding of the
Scriptures, it's going to
take a little bit of work to
understand the culture,
right, to fully understand
what's going on.
And I don't want that to
feel daunting because it's
not.
There's so many resources and
opportunities for us to
just get a little bit below
the surface to understand
what's going on in the
text.
Now, in a church full of
real people with real
lives, is anyone brave
enough to tell me, admit
to me that they like to
watch Saturday Night
Live?
Okay, we got some.
Thank you all very much.
You're brave.
You are brave people.
Saturday Night Live, these
sketches, they often
assume a base level of
cultural knowledge to get
the punchline, right?
Like, if we took somebody
from 1920 and had them
watch a modern episode of
Saturday Night Live,
probably not going to find
it that funny.
They might be able to
pick up on some of the
kind of, like, some of
the overarching things.
They might read into body
language and be like,
oh, all right, yeah.
But, like, if they don't
understand the culture,
they're going to miss it.
One of my favorite skits
from Saturday Night Live
happens to be Adam Sandler's
The Lunch Lady.
Yeah?
Now, if you take somebody,
no offense, because I know
some of you are in the room,
homeschoolers, you just don't
get it.
I'm sorry.
If you didn't stand in that
line and ask that lady with
the hairnet for an extra
scoop of navy beans, you
just don't get it.
There's parts of it that
you're going to understand
and that you're going to
get.
But if you're not careful,
you might miss it.
So, when approaching the
Bible, we can do so with
confidence knowing that God
inspired and preserved it for
us to understand.
But when we hit a
challenging passage or when
we hit something that seems
to be a contradiction, it's an
invitation to go deeper.
And my fear is that because many
of us have been subtly handed
this golden tablet view, whenever
we hit something that seems
difficult or challenging or
complex, we give up.
And we say, okay, this Bible isn't
what I thought it was.
Because I was told that it was
like this God divine thing fell
from the sky for me to read and
understand.
And I'm not getting it.
I see so many people give up on
the Scriptures instead of dig
deeper.
My personal experience on this
journey is that whenever I'm
faced with the opportunity,
going deeper has almost always
caused me to fall more deeply
in love with God.
And when it doesn't, because I've
been on this journey for long
enough, because I've allowed this
text to transform me from the
inside out, when it doesn't, when I
still don't have my questions
answered, I can walk away saying,
I trust the God who preserved
this for me.
Even if I don't have an answer
to this question right now, and
even if I might never get an
answer to this question right
now, I trust the God who is
faithful, who is kind, who is
loving, who is merciful.
I can trust the Father.
And this is my desire for us in
this room.
My desire is that we would have
such a relationship with the
Scriptures.
And how it introduces us to the
God who saves, that when we're
challenged, and when we find
difficulty, and when we get
confused, that in community by the
power of the Holy Spirit, we would
trust God with this text.
All right, lastly, I'm sorry, I'm
running late.
Wait, where are we at here?
Okay, lastly, yep, the purpose.
The purpose of the Bible.
What does the Bible say it's
intended to be used for?
All Scripture is breathed out by
God and useful to teach us what is
true, to make us realize what is
wrong in our lives, to correct us
when we are wrong, and teach us what
to do right.
God uses it to prepare and equip his
people to do every good work.
The final thing Paul says that
impacts how we approach the Bible is
that the Scripture is given to us.
It's intended to give us wisdom, to
know what is true, to believe what is
true, and to learn to live out that
truth in every area of our lives.
Now, here's the tension I see in
American Christianity, is rather than
seeing it as a book that's intended to
give us wisdom about what is true and
how to live in every area of our life,
is we'd rather approach it like a
black and white rule book, which gets
really confusing in parts of the Old
Testament and then in parts of the
New Testament, because there are
things that don't make that much
sense at all.
If this is a black and white rule
book, then every single woman in this
room who doesn't have her head
covered is sinning, right?
Or are we missing something?
I hope we're missing something, because
I don't want you all to have to wear
head coverings next week, right?
It's complex.
It's cultural.
These things matter.
It's not a black and white rule book.
It's intended to give us wisdom, to
know what is right in every situation.
The problem with using the Bible as a
rule book is you and I are always
going to find ourselves in situations
where there doesn't seem to be a
clear answer of what is right and what
is wrong.
And Paul says, Scripture is meant to
give us wisdom and a relationship with
the Holy Spirit so that we know what is
right in every situation.
The Bible is not intended to be a black
and white rule book.
It's intended to allow it to transform
us from the inside out.
So much more complex and beautiful than
a black and white rule book.
All right.
So if you have found yourself ever with
a shallow, confusing, or misunderstood
relationship with the Bible, you're not
alone.
The American church has had the tendency
to oversimplify what the Bible is and
how it should be used.
Please don't be discouraged and don't
give up.
Lean into the process.
Come talk to me.
Come talk to any one of our board
members.
Come talk to your small group leader.
I've had so many conversations with so many
people at our church that are diving deeper
into the Scriptures and finding a more
beautiful, more nuanced relationship with the
God who preserved it for them.
These words are God-spirited.
They're preserved for you and me, and they
lead to abundant and eternal life.
And this book is intended to be a lifelong
journey of learning and training and
correction that will transform us into the
people that God wants us to be for his
glory, for our good, and for the good of
our neighbors.
I want to end with a definition that Tim
Mackey from the Bible Project gives about
what the Bible is.
I think this is super helpful.
He says, the Bible is both divine and human
word that tells the truth about the story
of our world.
It is a unified library of literature from the
people of ancient Israel that all points to the
person of Jesus and how he is God's love,
salvation, and rescue to the world.
And it's not what you think it is.
It's actually way better than you could ever
imagine.
If you'd stand with me, I want to read
Psalms chapter 1, verses 1 through 3 over us.
I so resonate with what Tim said.
It's not what you think it is.
It's actually so much better.
And that's what the writer of Psalms chapter 1
is getting at.
He says this,
Oh, the joys of those who do not follow the
advice of the wicked or stand around with
sinners or join in with mockers, but they
delight in the law of the Lord.
Meditating on it day and night, they are like
trees planted along the river bank, bearing
fruit in each season.
Their lives never wither, their leaves never
wither, and they prosper in all they do.
Scriptures are an invitation to a life of
meditation and obedience.
My prayer for each one of us in this church is that we would
understand what it is, understand why it matters and
understand how to use it, and that we'd spend the rest of
our lives learning more about the God who made us and loves
us, and that we'd be equipped for every good work.
Let's pray.
Father, may we be a church who plants our trees by living water.
May we search the Scriptures with faithfulness and obedience to
you.
May you give us supernatural power to understand.
May you give us access to resources that help us understand the
cultural context and do so in a way that honors you, that gives you glory.
God, may we be a church of people that are rooted in the word and
submit it to the living word.
Root it in the written word, submit it to the living word for your
glory, for our good, for the good of our neighbors.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
We're dismissed, church.
Go in peace.
Amen.